Thank you guys for coming.
It's been a packed house all day.
If you haven't been to this room yet, this is all practical takeaway talks.
Nothing heady.
We don't need that.
Not here.
Maybe a little. I don't know.
We'll see. This is Edouard Maleix's.
He is going to talk about how AI for dev teams build
collective intelligence, which I think is on all of our minds today.
Can we give him a round of applause, please?
Just a second.
I will switch focus to not disturb so that you don't see
my notification.
So. Hi everyone.
As you noticed, I think today even more than before,
Agents are really everywhere in our work, in our conversation.
We have been talking with people and he's dropping conversation.
It seems like.
Yeah, it's what keeps us busy and we are preparing for
a, a new, a new shift
which will move agents from our isolated environment to teams working together.
So if agents
writes our code, review our code, even start to plan our sprint.
So move it towards management position.
It makes me wonder what our agents learn yesterday
that our team can use today or tomorrow and the days after.
So I want to share and help you find out.
Before.
Before we talk about any solution, I want to address the familiar obstacles.
You know, you have your you probably experimented
maybe with your agents that run pseudo autonomously.
You have Claude in auto mode, or
by running headless
or open.
If you're into that, even even though it seems like it has a bad publicity
today, all the small discoveries, all the tiny learnings, all the incidents
that are inside the session there rarely make it out of it.
They just end up closed here.
So corrections evaporate eventually.
And that's what we probably all did.
We start to create skills or rules or any piece of documentation
that can get injected inside the agent's context.
But then what happens?
You have lots of rule that piles up.
Some skills, some project notes.
And yeah, they dressed pile up.
Same as your contact widow.
It really gets crowded and you barely can barely say when it's getting used.
If it's still useful, if it became stale,
and even if it gets activated when you expect it to be activated.
So in the end, if we are in the context of engineering, when it's time
for the review of a given work to start,
maybe the PR can show up green.
Like all test passes,
you have some PR description, you follow the spec, you can hardly.
You cannot even tell actually what lessons shape that PR shape that work.
So I would imagine that this sounds a bit familiar, and I'm not an alien
when I say that.
So after thinking about it a little bit, I.
I've been thinking a dev.
Teams like humans and agents included,
they don't need just another Wikipedia, a wiki that you have in your teams.
They.
I don't think I've heard that dev teams should stay locked with their agent
in their fusional relationship, and apparently none of the speakers today
think so because it seems like, yeah, teams is really everywhere.
So agents work, create lessons every day
like you have, you have those lessons that are lessons
that capture in the session, but the teams is not learning.
So what could we do to get out of that?
That loop?
Well, I think that we need
a sort of knowledge factory, like, as the go, as the work go,
you have that system that catches mistake interruptions
and turns them into some guidance.
Then you check whether those guidance actually help.
Naturally, you will let
some of that some of those guidance fail because some knowledge just decay.
We have to accept that.
And that can happen when the model evolve, when your code base change.
So the idea is that instead of having static documentation,
we have something that constantly move live dies the diameter.
Not a problem. Just need to accept that.
So before I go a bit deeper in the theory
and the experiment, I won't tell you a bit where that comes from.
So that's me. I'm a freelance consultant.
I help tech leads and CTO
on authentication, application
performance, that productivity challenges.
And as I was helping some customers dev team to adopt coding
agents, I've been building.
An open source infrastructure and some set of tools to turn
those repeated friction that all the dev teams encounter into something that,
yeah, help teams on board in a common ground.
So what I want today is to share some of those learnings,
to share some of the primitives that I think could help in that way.
But beware, it's all very experimental.
Don't imagine that. I tell you, this is the way we should do it.
It's like everyone today we experiment in our way.
We try to find some places to put it in place and test it.
And here, that's the same with that,
with that framework.
So I think the solution should start at the low level.
And the lowest level I think is the change level. So
if, if we don't want the, the agents learning or the lessons
to just become some foreclosure, we need to track
who did the work when they did and what was the reasoning behind it,
what lessons, what knowledge they use to do those to make those decisions.
So we need some evidence to illustrate
that the sort of weird moment we are in that we float in.
That's a PR I opened a month ago for a festival plugin,
and knowing that the maintainer,
famous guy in the JS ecosystem was not really,
agent friendly at the time.
I just did my best to mask all traces from Claude Code.
So that PR was really written, I think 95% by Claude.
And I don't have a shame.
To assume that.
And it did the work.
I mean, I did my best to have, to have the agent writing good test.
That description is is fine enough, particularly the issue, the code as well.
And all the commits are under my name.
They have my even my GPG signature.
Wonderful.
And that PR under my name.
So the illusion is perfect.
But I think that's one of the problem that we should address.
Like right now who can assumes that work?
It's it's even worse for the PR reviews.
I guess you might have received some PR reviews
authored by one of your teammates, but actually authored by Claude Code.
Isn't it insulting? Well, I think that is.
And that's where I wanted to first start with that ground work
and give the agent an identity.
So that's the first primitive, the first building block,
the idea that entity gives us a clear, separate actor.
It gives us some sign commit.
And then at that stage, you already solve one small problem.
The agent does not hide behind your name or behind
a cloud codename or whatever.
And also it starts to create some sort of boundary,
because if the agent has its own identity, it has its own identifier,
it can have its own access rules, its own set of authorization.
And it starts it stops serving on your existing permission as a human.
So access control
is really about access control here, and it opens the way for that.
But of course identity is just the starting point.
It, it it starts the track of attribution.
It tells us who acted, but it does not tell us why
the action made sense at all at the time it was done.
That's where the second primitive comes, the diary.
So absolutely opinionated form of building blocks.
You could give it lots of name.
At some point I needed to give it a name and I think diary fit for
to describe the place where the stops being just the,
the work and the lesson stop being a throw away artifact.
So I read the home for the
for all the the discoveries, all the
what the f moment, all the decision making that happened during the work.
It's also the first
spot where you can also have some sort of access boundary that rotates.
For example, you could have your diary shared by your team,
the diary that could be purely personal for your style of work preferences,
all scope to repository or scoped to a project.
It's the first point where you can define those policies.
What matters in the end is that if the work or decision matters,
you need to land it somewhere before it disappears.
So in practice, this is what it could look like.
You would have your commit done by the agents.
So here linked to a GitHub application
you can see the bot.
With a reference to the entry
that capture the the procedure, the reasoning behind the work.
And then you can already start to do a bit less like guesswork.
You can start to go a bit further
than just the diff and and the, the commit messages.
You can start to have the rationale behind.
But that's also still just the beginning.
Now we need to find a way to capture the lessons
that the next session can reduce.
So that act start when you have to capture correction
and that the stop belong to one diff and become reusable knowledge.
But there is a long way there.
Before
I introduce how we could capture those incidents, I want to just,
create create a common ground over the standing.
So I will take an example of where an agent can stumble.
So and that's a true a true case.
So on Monday your agent update your Rest API
or whatever API, whatever contract you might have,
it remembers to regenerate the open API specs,
the TypeScript SDK that you have that also,
that is also derived from the open API specs, but
you also have a Go SDK in that code base and it completely missed it.
On Tuesday you have the same situation.
So my case I use the best French curse word.
And the agent promise that, okay, it won't happen again.
But you know the you know what follows on Wednesday.
You have the same trap, the Go client go stale again.
So of course, to be clear, this kind of example,
the CI should catch it and would catch it in the
in that in that case before it's even merge.
The point is not really here.
The idea is to save some iteration, because if you always have to wait
for some sort of post-processing to catch
the situation, well, in the meantime, before you had any commit and push,
the agent has been, for example, updating the test with outdated SDK.
So the idea is that we don't want to waste iteration,
we want stadium to know the practice like,
a human would do.
So here I will be a bit Captain
Obvious after all the work done today and all the discussion.
So why did the two day lesson never stick?
Well, simply because the the the correction that we did here to
to to remind the agent to generate the go to go
SDK, stay trapped in one session.
So the the the Wednesday agent, the Wednesday
session just doesn't know about it.
And that's the same for the team.
That's where it becomes a problem because not only my agent
would stumble on that, but also all the other teams.
Agent would also stumble on the same thing.
So what it does, it just falls back.
Luckily or unluckily, what's already in the context
or what the model already knows.
And yeah, here you just count on luck for the agent to to do the right decision.
No way to tell if that will be the right one.
So I said before the
the the knowledge lend in diary.
The diary.
Sorry, diary is a bit more granular.
Sorry, it's a bit more granular than that.
What you have inside it's entry.
So the entry will be used to describe different events to different events.
Sorry. So you will have four categories.
I'll let you read them to capture different type of situation.
For the case of the Tuesday
or Wednesday incident with the API story, it's an episodic entry.
It's what the f moment?
That's where it belongs and
that's where it should be captured.
And here's an example entry.
So that reminds me a little bit knowledge you need that
some other people talked about this morning here.
It was captured during
when the agent used the wrong driver the the wrong DB driver method,
which totally missed the transaction session.
That can be quite a mess if you if you can imagine no world back possible.
So you'd have a either duplicate right or whatever.
So here clearly not something that we want to keep doing at the next session.
So here this example entry is also linked to other entries.
And that's where it can become interesting because you have isolated
events that can be linked then between each other.
And here we have that entry that was created originally standalone,
but then we can link it to the PR review that made the notice, like say, hey,
what the fuck did you do? You don't use that.
Sorry for the query. I'm French.
Let myself go
so you can track both that PR command
and the fix
that is linked to that, so that it does not happen again.
And the idea is that six months
from now on, you can if you land on one of those entry,
you can also land on the fix and the lesson that goes with it.
So at this stage, yeah,
you already made some effort
to understand entry to have that framework.
So what you do at the stage actually is pretty simple.
It's passive accumulation.
You have that system in place that that workflow in place.
And you should have your agent that just capture
passively these entries, this incident, these lessons, this knowledge,
because that's when you have
enough entries that you can start to shape into something that really is helpful.
And the curation start by discovering what you have.
That's that becomes
honestly the bit, the magical moment, because you have no idea.
You cannot track all the entries that was done even less where
new team is large because it can come from everywhere.
Useful stuff, useless stuff.
So the idea is that you start to map a bit the territory, you start to find scopes,
you start then to slice those scope into some given incident.
For example, in my case, the database incident that I noticed
and then you expand those entries, you start to check the relationship
that they have.
And eventually if you have a hunch, you just do
raw search, like pure RAG.
And at some point when you have some
thematic entries, you can build some sort of pack of knowledge.
So back
that's a small created bundle of entries
that you should or eventually at some point your agent should pick
for one task for one really area.
So it's clearly not your children bags of toys.
So if you have parents who are over here,
I can you can imagine what's a bag of toys like lots of mess and call it a day.
It's tidy.
No, it's not like that.
More like a gallery exhibition.
Really?
You have to make sense with that bag.
So here, that's an example, a visual representation of one of those pack.
Actually, the first one related to database practice
in the project that I'm using to build.
So it's really just dog footing.
That was the first use case.
And every entry here that you can see, it's really, really example of stuff
that broke that are then reused to compose that pack.
But the pack
is not yet where the agent reads.
There is one more step before that.
And that step is really important and very sensitive. It's
at that stage.
So you have all those entries reference inside the pack
and you need to, to, to, to to answer yourself.
How will how will that how will I load that knowledge inside the agent.
So what you want to to do something out of the ordinary
I just imagine okay, let's just build some markdown files out of those raw,
those raw entries into something that can be really usable by an agent.
So this is typically another task assisted by
you will have the agent fetching the entries for
that are referenced in that bag, trims them eventually to fit a token budget.
And then
you can you can load that rendered back in the agent.
And what's very important here is that every section you can see
points to a given entry in every section, keep the attribution lives.
So here you can see the source with the entry identifier,
the human that was operating and the agent identifier as well.
So the idea is to really be able to not have just a skill that says that's
how you do things.
It's more like that's how you do things, because we got bitten somewhere that hurts
and we don't want we don't want that to happen again.
So to summarize that, that act to
we have now a sort of pipeline or even more loop,
the interruption becomes an entry, the right entries become a pack,
then the pack becomes something the agent can read.
And then in the end, the lesson that one developer paid for
or one autonomous agent paid for becomes a team asset.
Actually, it's
even there is even a discipline.
I did not hear the word yet today that seems to be called compound engineering.
So let's see if that happens and we hear more about it.
Now, the harder and more interesting
question is who decides
what survives?
What knowledge remains?
So in a human team, no one really decides alone.
You have some ADR or however we want to call them, some wikis.
The traces in the code reviews, some postmortems.
Eventually, sadly, that happens.
But that's now Reg moving at the human pace.
And now these days, we try to adapt our base to the agent base.
So when agent writes some tiny lessons all day long.
There is no feedback loop like that at least yet.
Not much.
It's just lots of individual initiatives getting built at these days,
and they produce correction faster than those systems can absorb them.
So that means we need some instruments to judge them.
So that will not be novelty, because today I think if you did not hear about it,
you learn a lot about evals. I guess
I will still talk about it, but I will go briefly, considering that
you already learn about it today and I don't want to waste your attention.
But here in our case, for those rendered packs, what we want to know
when evaluate is that is whether the the pack
is true to the entries.
Does it, does it transform the entries?
Does it include all of them?
Does it actually help on a really scenario?
So that's the most typical use case.
And the other thing that you would you want to know it's the activation.
It's it's to answer did the skill did not get loaded on time.
So here in that session we will just focus on fidelity and usefulness.
Before I go into the the process, there is something
a bit more technical I would like to spend time on
is the environment that those judges will run in.
I did not hear it much emphasized today, but maybe I just missed the good talk.
But I think all those agents task should run in a controlled environment.
And here what I
built for that case is just an environment that run in its own sandbox
a little bit like, thank you, a little bit like,
you could have with Codex and Box,
but here control the environment so you can decide
what files can be accessed.
You can decide also what, network calls can be done.
You really control that environment.
So there is no leak from the outside or inside out.
So that's where the LM works in that VM.
What's unique though.
It's for every task it's input.
So you have some prompt template some some set of criteria
that will allow us to sort of score or assess the result and some references.
And of course, we want to have some sort of context
that will be loaded in that in time, because that's the context
that will be used either to improve our agent.
But here in that case,
that's that context that will be judged, that will be assessed.
So here in that example for to
to to evaluate the field of those rendered packs,
we had those three simplified criteria
with their own binary score.
And the first look great. Yeah.
Composite score of almost one free win.
Free lunch okay I won I'm a genius.
But actually, if you spend a little bit of time on evil,
you can see that lazy prompt or badly
calibrated criteria can just backfire and be giving a false sense of safety.
So to call it a short,
the idea is that before you run an LLM judge, you you are the judge.
You do the work that the judge will do yourself,
and you check if those criteria would really match and catch something.
And same for the prompt.
It should reflect your own questioning, your own way to score things.
Now about usefulness.
So okay, we can say now that, the, the, the,
the agent did not lie about the pack, the knowledge that was created.
But now we want to see if it's really useful.
So here I will also keep it short because if you heard about it.
But the idea is that you give your agent runtime a task
that we produce some of those incidents that you already add.
So that's good
because if you already captured the incident,
you already have the situation, you already have the context.
And that's where it's really good because you should it's
it becomes really difficult if you invent task or catch them from the past.
It's much easier if you already know the incident,
the story behind it and the task.
So here, that's one of those tasks to catch up
and reproduce that go incident that goes missing.
And we run that
with the context.
We run it again with the context.
So that rendered pack that gives the agent knowledge and what matters is that delta.
And so you have then an average and that will run the judge
to score based on those criteria.
So of course here
I want to show you a success story, but that's a new and one.
The idea is that for that go
client scenario without a pack, we fail at 67 every time the go
SDK was missing from the agent's work, whereas with the pack
it was always passing, even after repeating
that same task.
So the idea is that
you don't repeat the same mistake,
you just use those pack
to to feed the agent the right now.
I don't know how much I have remaining.
I will keep it very short.
Now, the last the last act, if we consider that we have Adrian that are getting
autonomous, that can learn by themselves and inject knowledge by themselves,
what stop us in some way is to get ready to make agents fully autonomous.
And like one of the talk mentioned earlier,
there is a big vanity thing here because the agent is really tempted
to please us, and it's quite pleasing
actually, to have the agent that please us and answer in our direction.
So I think one of the first psychological, psychological limit
is just to, to forget about, that concept of having someone that always,
like you have the good suggestion, you need to get rid of that if you want to
go to the path of having autonomous agent.
And once you
get rid of that, you can start to consider to have task
being created automatically, like, some agent.
That's awesome.
So that create those tasks like
do this, do this, fulfill this issue or do this PR review.
And you have that big bucket with lots of tasks and you do some voluntary
work.
The idea is that you don't assign any task.
You just have agent with some set of capabilities,
and any of those agents
can file a task if it matches is is capability.
So it really picks voluntarily.
And then what's interesting is that
if you build on top of the previous work,
all those autonomous task always keep attribution alive.
So it means that you build even faster knowledge, build even faster correction.
So what matter is just that you as the human, keep the goal, the judgment
and the responsibility, and the agents keep the continuity, the repetition,
the buffer, some work,
and if that infrastructure exists, can imagine that
identity that grows even more like in more interesting direction.
You could have dedicated coder agents, some critic agents, some
maybe management agents.
The idea that you can specialize agent that will pick the task
and promise that they will fulfill it properly,
and then you can enable some sort of trust because those agents specialize
a bit like individual contributors and companies.
So to conclude, I will just leave you with that question.
So what did your agents learn yesterday that you still
that your team still knows today?
And to finish a bit of self promo,
if you are curious or interested and want to have a look at that experiment
I mention, you can scan the QR code that will lead you to the repository.
That that that is just the whole infrastructure that I mentioned.
So if you want to comment it, toast it, roast it, however you want to do it,
please do.
And if you try it, let me know what broke what does not work.
And that's it.
Thanks for your attention.
Thank you so much for that.
We have two minutes for questions
if anyone would like to ask anything.
Thanks for the great talk.
Couple of questions.
Is this parallel to Palace
or is there ideas similar to many Palace or.
There is one component the memory part.
But honestly, I did not spend most of my time.
Refining how how best the memory works, how best is stored,
and how best it can be retrieved.
Because for me, what matters more is that it's providing the primitives
and the tools for the complete workflow.
Because I don't think memory in isolation is
can answer that problem of of sharing knowledge between teams.
One last one is I think the examples you showed
is pretty good, but in the life of a developer, it's
not as simple as fix and the new attribute.
And then there's a bit of a chain of it.
It's a lot more nuanced than that when you started using it yourself.
Did you come across edge cases or nuances where that simple pattern
might not work and you needed to do some more complicated?
I mean, it's it's not as instant instantaneous as I might make it appear.
That entry that captured the incident, it's still there.
It lives.
And the fix probably won't land on the same day.
So clearly the entry is just here to stay.
And here it's about having your workflow that will have the intelligence
to pick the incident that already exist and compare with what already exists.
Because sometimes it's just good to just accept that there is an incident,
and if it does not, if there is no recurrence, you don't care.
It's just a one time one off.
But if it happens more often,
then it's time to indeed create some relationship and consolidate.
Maybe your workflow. Okay, cool. Thank you.
Thank you.
Any more takers for questions?
Thank you so much for the talk.
I think it was really interesting.
And I think the question I have is how do you approach kind of managing
and maintaining this knowledge base as your code base and product evolve?
And maybe something that was true like a month ago is no longer true.
Nice one.
Honestly, not not has much different if you already use skills
or these sort of things, it's it's very similar in a way,
because you have all those entries that you don't really bother.
I said, you just accumulate that knowledge.
And it's when you start
to build some actual rendered pack
that it becomes similar to what you already have,
because those rendered facts, they are just skills.
In the end, they are markdown file that are then converted to skills,
so you maintain them
kind of the same way as you would maintain skill in the modern workflow.
So you have to run some regular evals with the model that your team is using.
If they are not useful enough or do not bring any benefit, then it dies.
And if it still keep bringing it, if it's bringing benefits, then you you keep it.
That answer the question.
Yeah,
partially.
Ranges from how is it still mango?
Or if.
It's a mix that curation you will start manually at first because
first of all you need to get use this a new it's a new habit, a new workflow.
And I think every workflow before we should lend it to an LLM,
we need to master it as human, because then you need to explain that
LLM how we should do things, and if you are not able to explain it.
How can we expect an LM to do it for you.
So you have the creation starts manually,
assisted by agent to fetch all the things that you would want to discover.
And once you start to understand the pattern,
then you can start to delegate that curation as well to agents.
So that's how it works in practice.
Cool.
If you guys have any more questions, I'm sure you can find Edward out and about.
Thank you so much. Appreciate you.
Thanks for the tension.
It is now coffee break time, so go get